Total chunks: 256
0: A Comprehensive Overview of Large Language Models Humza Naveeda, Asad Ullah Khana,∗, Shi Qiub,∗, Muhammad Saqibc,d,∗, Saeed Anware,f, Muhammad Usmane,f, Naveed Akhtarg,i, Nick Barnesh, Ajmal Miani aUniversity of Engineering and Technology (UET), Laho
1: ese works encompass diverse topics such as architectural innovations, better training strategies, context length improvements, fine-tuning, multi-modal LLMs, robotics, datasets, benchmarking, efficiency, and more. With the rapid development of techni
2: ts from extensive informative summaries of the existing works to advance the LLM research. Keywords: Large Language Models, LLMs, chatGPT, Augmented LLMs, Multimodal LLMs, LLM training, LLM Benchmarking 1. Introduction Language plays a fundamental ro
3: d Ullah Khan), shiqiu@cse.cuhk.edu.hk (Shi Qiu), muhammad.saqib@data61.csiro.au (Muhammad Saqib), saeed.anwar@kfupm.edu.sa (Saeed Anwar), muhammad.usman@kfupm.edu.sa (Muhammad Usman), naveed.akhtar1@unimelb.edu.au (Naveed Akhtar), nick.barnes@anu.edu
4: aMDA T0 (Oct) ChatGPT (Nov) Sparrow (Sep) FLAN-U-PaLM (Oct) Bard (Oct) MT-NLG (Jan) AlphaCode (Feb) Chinchilla (Mar) PaLM (Apr) U-PALM (Oct) BLOOM (Nov) AlexaTM (Aug) PaLM2 (May) GPT-4 PanGu-Σ (Mar) BloombergGPT Claude Gemini (Dec) Figure 2: Chronolo
5: . While conventional language modeling (LM) trains task-specific mod- els in supervised settings, PLMs are trained in a self-supervised setting on a large corpus of text [7, 8, 9] with the aim of learning a generic representation that is shareable am
6: ine-tuning. LLMs accurately respond to task queries when prompted with task descriptions and examples. However, pre-trained LLMs fail to follow user intent and perform worse in zero-shot set- tings than in few-shot. Fine-tuning them with task instruc
7: ted in these areas either by task-specific training [25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31] or better prompting [32]. The LLMs abilities to solve diverse tasks with human-level performance come at a cost of slow training and inference, extensive hardware requir
8: a comprehensive yet concise overview of the general direction of LLM research. This arti- cle summarizes architectural and training details of pre-trained LLMs and delves deeper into the details of concepts like fine- tuning, multi-modal LLMs, augmen
9: o seven branches: 1. Pre-Training 2. Fine-Tuning 3. Efficient 4. Inference 5. Evaluation 6. Applications 7. Challenges hensively, including background, pre-training, fine-tuning, multi-modal LLMs, augmented LLMs, LLMs-powered agents, datasets, evalua
10: ges and future directions, and conclusion in sections 7 and 8, re- spectively. 3  2. Background We provide the relevant background to understand the fun- damentals related to LLMs in this section. We briefly discuss necessary components in LLMs and r
11: ositional embedding vector is added to the token embedding. Variants of positional embedding include absolute, relative, or learned positional encodings. Within rel- ative encoding, Alibi and RoPE are two widely used positional embeddings in LLMs. Al
12: below. Self-Attention [64]: Calculates attention using queries, keys, and values from the same block (encoder or decoder). Cross Attention: It is used in encoder-decoder architectures, where encoder outputs are the queries, and key-value pairs come f
13: Error Linear Unit (GeLU) is the combination of ReLU, dropout [72] and zoneout [73]. GLU variants [74]: The Gated Linear Unit [75] is a neural network layer that is an element-wise product (⊗) of a linear transformation and a sigmoid transformed (σ) l
14: s section describes distributed LLM training approaches briefly. More details are available in [13, 37, 80, 81]. Data Parallelism: Data parallelism replicates the model on multiple devices where data in a batch gets divided across de- vices. At the e
15: hile keeping the communication costs as low as possible. 4  2.7. Libraries Some commonly used libraries for LLMs training are: Transformers [82]: The library provides access to various pre- trained transformer models with APIs to train, fine-tune, in
16: y Facebook AI Re- search lab (FAIR) to build deep learning models. The main features of PyTorch include a dynamic computation graph and a pythonic coding style. Tensorflow [88]: A deep learning framework written by Google. The key features of TensorF
17: Duplicated data can affect model per- formance and increase data memorization; therefore, to train LLMs, data deduplication is one of the preprocessing steps. This can be performed at multiple levels, like sentences, documents, and datasets. Privacy 
18: and passes the intermediate representation to the decoder to generate the output. Here, the encoder sees the complete sequence utilizing self-attention whereas the decoder processes the sequence one after the other with implementing cross-attention. 
19: reas- ing the computational cost by activating only a few experts at a time [91, 92]. 2.10. Pre-Training Objectives This section describes LLMs pre-training objectives. For more details see the paper [93]. Full Language Modeling: An autoregressive la
20: f tokens) are masked randomly and the model is asked to predict masked tokens given the past and future context. An example is shown in Figure 5. Unified Language Modeling: Unified language modeling [94] is a combination of causal, non-causal, and ma
21: , from pre-training to fine-tuning for downstream tasks and utilization. An example of different training stages and in- ference in LLMs is shown in Figure 6. In this paper, we refer to alignment-tuning as aligning with human preferences, while occas
22: spond to user queries effectively, the pre-trained model is fine-tuned on in- struction formatted data i.e., instruction and an input-output pair. Instructions generally comprise multi-task data in plain natural language, guiding the model to respond
23: 00] for model alignment. In RLHF, a fine-tuned model on demonstrations is further trained with reward model- ing (RM) and reinforcement learning (RL), shown in Figure 6. Below we briefly discuss RM and RL pipelines in RLHF. Reward modeling: trains a 
24: g on data containing different prompt styles [16, 101, 102]. A good guide on prompt engineering is available at [32]. Below, we will discuss various widely used prompt setups. Zero-Shot Prompting: LLMs are zero-shot learners and ca- pable of answerin
25: cuss various prompting techniques for reasoning below. Chain-of-Thought (CoT): A special case of prompting where demonstrations contain reasoning information aggregated with inputs and outputs so that the model generates outcomes with step-by-step re
26: tonomous agents. 3. Large Language Models This section reviews LLMs, briefly describing their architec- tures, training objectives, pipelines, datasets, and fine-tuning details. 3.1. Pre-Trained LLMs Here, we provide summaries of various well-known p
27: he training as it produces shorter sequences. After pre-training, the model is fine-tuned using adapter layers [106] for downstream tasks. GPT-3 [6]: The GPT-3 architecture is the same as the GPT- 2 [5] but with dense and sparse attention in transfor
28: s. To avoid over-fitting or under-fitting for a language, mT5 employs a data sampling procedure to select samples from all languages. The paper suggests using a small amount of pre-training datasets, including all languages when fine-tuning for a tas
29: he first stage and then adding English and Chinese data. This trained model gets duplicated multiple times to initialize the 198B MoE model. Moreover, to use the model for downstream tasks, CPM-2 experimented with both com- plete fine-tuning and prom
30: primar- ily focused on the Chinese language. It claims to train on the largest Chinese text corpora for LLM training, and achieved state-of-the-art in 54 Chinese NLP tasks. Jurassic-1 [112]: A pair of auto-regressive language mod- els, including a 7B
31: lected from the Internet. A Massive Data Filtering System (MDFS) built on Spark is developed to pro- cess the raw data via coarse and fine filtering techniques. To speed up the training of Yuan 1.0 to save energy expenses and carbon emissions, variou
32: ger model with 26x the number of parameters of the latter. This bigger model outperformed other state-of-the- art models in 68 NLP tasks. LLMs produce text with incorrect facts. In order to have control of the generated text with fac- tual consistenc
33: ut performance degradation. As opposed to GPT-3, which uses dense and sparse layers, GPT-NeoX-20B uses only dense layers. The hyperparameter tuning at this scale is difficult; therefore, the model chooses hyperparameters from the method [6] and inter
34: tes1 library. These changes stabilize training with improved downstream performance. GLaM [91]: Generalist Language Model (GLaM) represents a family of language models using a sparsely activated decoder- only mixture-of-experts (MoE) structure [121, 
35: me dataset as the Gopher [116] but with a little different data sampling distribution (sampled from MassiveText). The model architec- ture is similar to the one used for Gopher, with the exception of AdamW optimizer instead of Adam. Chinchilla identi
36: and is later unfrozen for end-to-end training. The model is trained on a combination of denoising and causal language modeling (CLM) objectives, concatenat- ing a [CLM] token at the beginning for mode switching. Dur- ing training, the CLM task is app
37: ined for larger iterations on a better quality dataset. PaLM- 2 shows significant improvements over PaLM, while reducing training and inference costs due to its smaller size. To lessen toxicity and memorization, it appends special tokens with a fract
38: noiser: which corrupts a large number of tokens randomly. During pre- training, UL2 includes a denoiser token from R, S, X to rep- resent a denoising setup. It helps improve fine-tuning perfor- mance for downstream tasks that bind the task to one of 
39: struction tuning. LLaMA-1 [127]: Implements efficient causal attention [128] by not storing and computing masked attention weights and key/query scores. Another optimization is reducing the number of activations recomputed in the backward pass, as in
40: c models and reduces catastrophic forget- ting effects in the case of continual learning. 3.1.2. Coding CodeGen [130]: CodeGen has similar architecture to PaLM [15], i.e., parallel attention, MLP layers, and RoPE em- beddings. The model is trained on
41: ly to this, Codex generates 100 versions of a program by repetitive sampling for a given description, which produces a working solution for 77.5% of the problems passing unit tests. Its powerful version powers Github Copilot2. AlphaCode [132]: A set 
42: e the performance of AlphaCode, simulated programming competitions are hosted on the Codeforces platform: overall, AlphaCode ranks at the top 54.3% among over 5000 competitors, where its Codeforces rating is within the top 28% of recently participate
43: StarCoder trains an encoder to filter names, emails, and other personal data from the training data. Its fine- tuned variant outperforms PaLM, LLaMA, and LAMDA on HumanEval and MBPP benchmarks. 3.1.3. Scientific Knowledge Galactica [138]: A large cur
44: a is in English. LaMDA is trained with the objective of producing re- sponses that exhibit high levels of quality, safety, and grounded- ness. To achieve this, discriminative and generative fine-tuning techniques are incorporated to enhance the model
45: ation of general purpose, financial, general purpose instructions, and financial institutions datasets. Xuan Yuan 2.0 combined the pre-training and fine-tuning stages to avoid catastrophic forgetting. 3.2. Fine-Tuned LLMs Pre-trained LLMs have excell
46: eated Datasets Numerous hand-crafted instruction-tuning datasets with different design choices are proposed in the literature to instruction-tune LLMs. The performance of fine-tuned LLMs depends on multiple factors, such as dataset, instruction diver
47: OPT-IML [97] and Flan [16] curated larger 2k and 1.8k task datasets, respectively. While increasing task size alone is not enough, OPT-IML and Flan add more prompting setups in their datasets, zero-shot, few-shot, and CoT. In continuation, CoT Collec
48: dels. Models Findings & Insights T5 • Encoder and decoder with shared parameters perform equivalently when parameters are not shared • Fine-tuning model layers (adapter layers) work better than the conventional way of training on only classification 
49: t) for the model ERNIE 3.0 • A modular LLM architecture with a universal representation module and task-specific representa- tion module helps in the finetuning phase • Optimizing the parameters of a task-specific representation network during the fi
50: xhibit contrasting behavior in zero-shot and few-shot learning Gopher • Relative encodings enable the model to evaluate for longer sequences than training. ERNIE 3.0 Titan • Additional self-supervised adversarial loss to distinguish between real and 
51: ing research on LLMs • A working memory token approach can achieve strong performance over existing methods on mathematical MMLU and MATH benchmarks. It sets a new state-of-the-art on several downstream tasks such as PubMedQA (77.6%) and MedMCQA dev 
52: eness and efficiency, a transformer model can be asymmetrically constructed with a shallower encoder and a deeper decoder • To achieve better performances, it is necessary to employ strategies such as massively scaling upsampling, followed by the fil
53: which means larger models are likely to perform better AlexaTM • Encoder-decoder architecture is more suitable to train LLMs given bidirectional attention to the context than decoder-only • Causal Language Modeling (CLM) task can be added to benefit 
54: onstant performance improvement is observed when scaling the model • Smaller models can achieve good performances with more training data and computing time PanGu-Σ • Sparse models provide the benefits of large models at a lower computation cost • Ra
55: odel to follow instructions without fine-tuning LLaMA-2 • Model trained on unfiltered data is more toxic but may perform better on downstream tasks after fine-tuning • Model trained on unfiltered data requires fewer samples for safety alignment PaLM-
56: imitation learning and reinforcement learning • Generating answers with references can make labelers easily judge the factual accuracy of answers Tk-INSTRUCT • Instruction tuning leads to a stronger generalization of unseen tasks • More tasks improve
57: enough, training datasets should also be proportional for better generalization/performance • Fully held-out and partially supervised tasks performance improves by scaling tasks or categories whereas fully supervised tasks have no effect • Including 
58: • Instruction fine-tuning improves usability which otherwise is challenging for pre-trained models • Improving the model’s performance with instruction tuning is compute-efficient • Multitask prompting enables zero-shot generalization abilities in LL
59: re a few general-purpose fine-tuned models, where Alpaca is trained on 52k samples from text- davinci-003, Vicuna on 70k samples from ShareGPT.com, and LLaMA-GPT-4 by re-creating Alpaca instructions from GPT-4. Goat [151] fine-tunes LLaMA for arithme
60: man preferences into LLMs presents a significant advantage in mitigating undesirable behaviors and ensuring accurate outputs. The initial work on alignment, such as InstructGPT [20] aligns GPT-3 using a 3-step approach, instruction-tuning, reward mod
61: assists humans more effectively, which increases trust in the model’s output. Similar to the RLHF training style, a reward model is trained to rank generated responses containing web citations in answers to questions, which is later used to train the
62: ood of preferred against unpreferred responses, with per-sample importance weight. Reward ranked fine-tuning RAFT [159] fine-tunes the model on ranked responses by the reward model. Preference ranking optimization (PRO) [161] and RRHF [160] penalize 
63: ] prompts the LLM with ICL examples, instructing the LLM about what the response should contain to be considered useful and ethical. The same LLM is later fine-tuned with the new dataset. Aligning with Prompts: LLMs can be steered with prompts to gen
64: s used to fine-tune models for safety. While red-teaming largely relies on human annotators, another work [170] red-team LLMs to find prompts that lead to harmful outputs for other LLMs. 3.2.4. Continue Pre-Training Although fine-tuning boosts a mode
65: rmance with less data, existing literature [173, 174] finds that models trained on less data can outperform models trained with more data. In [173], 25% of the total downstream data is found enough for state-of-the-art performance. Selecting coreset-
66: unable to perform zero-shot extrapolation. A larger context length has benefits such as a better understanding of longer documents, more samples in in-context learning, execution of bigger rea- soning processes, etc. Expanding context length during f
67: ilated attention, reduces the computation cost significantly. LongT5 [48] proposes transient global atten- tion (TGlobal), applying attention to local and global tokens (windowed token averaging). The model replaces attention in T5 [10] with TGlobal 
68: ion fine-tuning. Extrapolation without Training: LM-Infinite [176] and par- allel context windows (PCW) [180] show length extrapolation is possible using pre-trained LLMs. LM-Infinite suggested Λ- shaped attention applied within the original context 
69: he query [54, 32], here we specifi- cally refer to the methods that access external storage program- matically, calling them augmented LLMs. The literature suggests various external memory designs to aug- ment LLMs, long-term [181, 182, 183, 184], sh
70: ly answer with references and utilize more informa- tion. With retrieval augmentation, smaller models have been shown to perform at par with larger models. For instance, the 11B model can become competitive to 540B PaLM in [25] and 7.5B to 280B Gophe
71: ghts unchanged and uses BM25 [192], nearest neighbors, or frozen pre-trained models like Bert [7] as a retriever. The retrieved information is provided as input to the model for response generation, shown to improve performance over LLMs without retr
72: ed transformer (RETRO) [183] shows pre-training smaller LLMs with RAG pipeline outper- forms larger LLMs, such as GPT-3 trained without RAG. RETRO uses a 2-trillion token subset of MassiveText as a database. The retrieval pipeline divides the input q
73: or ICL samples retrieval. REPLUG [199] trains the retriever with supervised signals from the frozen LLM-generated outputs. Training Retriever and LLM: Further benefits are achieved by training both the retriever and the model in [25, 200, 201]. In th
74: lable on the internet, which gets updated regularly. Rather than storing information locally, various methods retrieve query-related context through a web search and forward it to LLMs [203, 204, 156]. 3.4.2. Tool Augmented LLMs While RAG relies on t
75: shows tool documentation is enough to teach LLMs to use tools without demonstrations. RestGPT [209] integrates LLMs with RESTful APIs by decomposing tasks into planning and API selection steps. The API selector understands the API documentation to se
76: utilize different modules iteratively, such as retriever, tool execution, read-write to memory, feedback, etc., depending on the task. data generation pipeline with GPT-4 by providing in-context examples retrieved from API documentation. Tool augment
77: on →Execute →Inspect → Generate, to respond to the user query. Here, the database of tools is rich in modalities, including text, images, etc. Many of the multimodal tool augmentation systems employ multimodal LLMs [31, 215, 214, 206], while others u
78: imal to no fine-tuning". Below we summarize the re- search in LLMs-based autonomous agents. For a more detailed discussion, please refer to [220, 221]. LLMs Steering Autonomous Agents: LLMs are the cognitive controllers of the autonomous agents. They
79: pted with a task description and a sequence of actions, they can accurately generate plan ac- tions without any fine-tuning [222]. Reasoning via planning (RAP) [223] incorporates a re-purposed LLM as a world model to reason about future outcomes and 
80: dition to internal memory, various systems em- ploy external memory to save the response history. Reflex- ion [185] maintains an episodic memory to use previous re- sponses as feedback to improve future decision-making. Retro- former [224] improves i
81: sk operations. LLM (Say) builds a high-level plan to complete the task and a learned affordance function (Can) explores the possibility of executing the plan in the real world. SayCan uses RL to train the language-conditioned affordance function. PaL
82: facilities, and residences. 3.6. Efficient LLMs Deploying LLMs in production is expensive. Reducing their running costs while preserving performance is an appealing area of research. This section summarizes the approaches sug- gested to enhance LLMs’
83: er is a sequence of feature downscaling, non-linearity, and upscaling [106]. Variants of adapter tuning inject adapter layers sequentially [106] and in parallel [38], whereas the mixture of adapter (AdaMix) [239] employs multiple adapter modules in a
84: cific fixed discrete prompts are concatenated with input em- beddings in [40]. As discrete prompts bring instability, prompts are encoded through a learnable mapping in P-Tuning [237], naming continuous prompts, which are appended with the dis- crete
85: ffective in BitFit [244]. This method achieves full fine-tuning performance for tasks with less training data and comparable performance with more training data. 3.6.2. Quantization LLMs require extensive computing and memory for infer- ence. Deployi
86: 8-bit for remaining features. The lower pre- cision multiplication outputs are converted to FP-16 and con- catenated with others. The quantized models have homogenous word embeddings, which may degrade their performance. To fix this, token-level know
87: n error. To improve speed and per- formance, OPTQ updates weights in arbitrary order, employs 20  Figure 14: Illustration of parameter-efficient fine-tuning paradigms, where x is input and h is hidden state, figure courtesy [38]. Parallel adapter and
88: nd fine-tunes only quantization scaling parameters. LLM- QAT [252] generates training data from the pre-trained network and trains a quantized student model with knowledge distilla- tion. QLoRA [251] fine-tunes 4-bit quantized pre-trained LLM with Lo
89: ess im- portant weights without maintaining any structure. Existing LLM pruning methods take advantage of the unique charac- teristics of LLMs, uncommon for smaller models, where a small subset of hidden states are activated with large magni- tude [2
90: d in groups, rows, columns, or matrices, which speeds up the inference because of effective hardware tensor core utiliza- tion [255]. LLM-Pruner [42] employs a 3-stage structured pruning strategy, identifying the groups of hidden states caus- ing eac
91: tion from various modal- ities, MLLMs can achieve a deeper understanding of context, leading to more intelligent responses infused with a variety of expressions. Importantly, MLLMs align closely with human perceptual experiences, leveraging the syner
92: ich are collected from pre-trained and frozen visual encoder and LLM, respectively. Moreover, BLIP- 2 [260] proposes a two-stage strategy to pre-train a Querying Transformer (Q-Former) for the alignment between vision and language modalities: in the 
93: ion-following data for fine-tuning [58]. To ad- dress this issue, the solutions of benchmark adaptation [269, 271, 272], self-instruction [19, 31, 273], and hybrid composi- tion [274, 270] are employed, respectively. To mitigate the gap between the o
94: ctly updates the model parameters given task-specific datasets, the prompting technique provides certain context, ex- amples, or instructions to the model, fulfilling specialized tasks without changing the model parameters. Since prompting can signif
95: complex tasks into sub-tasks [279, 280]. Visual Reasoning Application: Recent visual reasoning sys- tems [281, 282, 206, 283] tend to apply LLMs for better visual information analysis and visual-language integration. Differ- ent from previous works [
96: antic scale of LLMs, minor changes in archi- tecture and training strategies have a big impact on performance and stability. Here, we summarize key architectural modules used in various LLMs, leading to better performance, reduced training time and m
97: ormance after fine-tuning. Positional Encoding: Like other building blocks of the model, positional encoding also affects the performance and training stability of LLMs. BLOOM [13] finds ALiBi outperforms learned and rotary positional encodings. Cont
98: d with this change and it makes the train- ing efficient allowing larger batch sizes. Multi-query attention is used in [15, 132]. Mixture of Experts: This type of architecture enables eas- ily scaling models to trillions of parameters [92, 91]. Only 
99: egrade the model’s performance [67]. How- ever, more experiments are required to verify this statement. 3.8.2. Training Strategies Training models at a huge scale require tricks to reduce train- ing costs, avoid loss divergence, and achieve better pe
100: ion in LLMs is limited. Training Instability: Loss divergence or spiking is a common issue in LLMs that occurs multiple times during training. This happens in the presence of gradient clipping [15]. To mitigate this problem, many approaches suggest r
101: ight initialization leads to unstable training, hence validating small initialization scheme [288]. Various models perform random weight initial- ization which can cause bad initialization, Galactica [138] sug- gests a longer warmup to negate the eff
102: elism and apply 5D paral- lelism which additionally contains optimizer parallelism and rematerialization. Mode Switching: It adds task-related tokens at the beginning of the text during training. These tokens refer to the natural language understandi
103: ce they have not yet outper- formed models trained in supervised settings. The supervised trained models are still state-of-the-art in various NLP tasks by a large margin as shown in [6, 15, 18]. 3.8.4. Zero-Shot vs Few-Shot LLMs perform well in zero
104: well for different tasks, for example, encoder-only for NLU tasks, decoder-only for NLG, and encoder-decoder for sequence2sequence model- ing. Encoder-only models are famous for smaller models such as Bert [7], RoBERTa [289], etc., whereas LLMs are e
105: encoder-decoder architecture with multiple training ob- jectives for different tasks, activating the encoder, decoder, or both according to the tasks. These variations in architecture and training objectives allow a model to perform well in differ- e
106: ble 7. These details are not as important as others to mention for instruction-tuned models, and are not provided by the papers. 5. Datasets and Evaluation Generating training and evaluation datasets is expensive be- cause of the large-scale data dem
107: rate, and interact with human language across a spectrum of tasks. Evaluating a language model (LM) is divided into two broader categories: 1) natural language un- derstanding (NLU) and 2) natural language generation (NLG). It is emphasized that task
108: w of evaluation datasets, we briefly discuss a few famous datasets within each category and offer a comprehensive list of datasets in Table 9. Moreover, we show a detailed overview of the train- ing datasets and evaluation tasks and benchmarks used b
109: self-supervised learn- ing. BIG-bench [298]: The BIG-bench (Behavior of Intelligent Generative Models Benchmark) is a large-scale benchmark de- signed to test the abilities of LLMs across a wide range of tasks, including reasoning, creativity, ethics
110: ons such as using in-house GPUs or getting a discounted rate, re-training, number of employees working on the problem, etc. “Training Parallelism” indicates distributed training using data parallelism (D), tensor parallelism (T), pipeline parallelism
111: ✓ 260k 1.1TB Heur+Dedup 2048 Ascend 910 - - D+OP+P+O+R MindSpore CPM-2 [12] AI Open'21 MIT Tsinghua General 198B ✓ 1M 2.6TB Dedup - - - - D+M JAXFormer Codex [131] arXiv'21 - OpenAI Coding 12B × - 100B Heur - - - - - - ERNIE 3.0 [110] arXiv'21 - Baid
112: [13] arXiv'22 RAIL-1.0 BigScience General 176B ✓ - 366B Dedup+PR 384 80G A100 2520h 3.87 Mil D+T+P Megatron+DS Galactica [138] arXiv'22 Apache-2.0 Meta Science 120B × 225k 106B Dedup 128 80GB A100 - - - Metaseq GLaM [91] ICML'22 - Google General 1.2T
113: [33] ICLR'23 Apache-2.0 Multiple General 130B × - 400B - 768 40G A100 1440h 3.37 Mil M - CodeGen [130] ICLR'23 Apache-2.0 Salesforce Coding 16B ✓ 650k 577B Heur+Dedup - TPU v4 - - D+M JAXFormer LLaMA [127] arXiv'23 - Meta General 65B × 350k 1.4T Clf+
114: bbreviations are the same as Table 3. Entries in “Data/Tokens” starting with “S-” represents the number of training samples. Models Publication Venue License Type Model Creators Purpose No. of Params Commercial Use Pre-trained Models Steps Trained Da
115: paca [148] Github'23 Apache-2.0 Stanford General 13B ✓ LLaMA 3-Epoch S-52k 8 80G A100 3h 600 FSDP PyTorch Vicuna [149] Github'23 Apache-2.0 LMSYS General 13B ✓ LLaMA 3-Epoch S-125k - - - - FSDP PyTorch LIMA [175] arXiv'23 - Meta+ General 65B - LLaMA 
116: it a rigorous test for mod- els’ ability to handle a wide range of topics and conversational contexts. WiC [307]: This dataset assesses a model’s ability to dis- cern word meanings based on context, aiding in tasks related to Word Sense Disambiguatio
117: Dec Next Token Dense+Sparse - - Layer Learned GeLU ✓ 96 96 12288 mT5 (13B) Enc-Dec Span Corruption Standard 250k SentencePiece Pre-RMS Relative ReLU - - - - PanGu-α (200B) Causal-Dec Next Token Standard 40k BPE Layer - - - 64 128 16384 CPM-2 (198B) E
118: er Rotary GeLU ✓ 44 64 - OPT (175B) Causal-Dec Next Token Standard - BPE - - ReLU ✓ 96 96 - BLOOM (176B) Causal-Dec Next Token Standard 250k BPE Layer ALiBi GeLU ✓ 70 112 14336 Galactica (120B) Causal-Dec Next Token Standard 50k BPE+custom Layer Lear
119: B) Non-Causal-Dec MoD Parallel+Multi-query 256k SentencePiece Layer RoPE SwiGLU × 118 48 18432 UL2 (20B) Enc-Dec MoD Standard 32k SentencePiece - - - - 64 16 4096 GLM (130B) Non-Causal-Dec AR Blank Infilling Standard 130k SentencePiece Deep RoPE GeGL
120: t, C4 offers billions of to- kens from web-crawled data. It is a comprehensive resource for training advanced Transformer models on various languages. LCQMC [310]: The Large-scale Chinese Question Matching Corpus (LCQMC) is a dataset for evaluating t
121: QA [330]: A dataset that probes the physical knowledge of models, aiming to understand how well they are learning about the real world. TriviaQA [331]: A dataset that tests models on reading com- prehension and open domain question answering (QA) tas
122: . Contextual Language Understanding RACE [337]: The RACE dataset is a reading comprehension dataset collected from English examinations in China, which benchmarks AI models for understanding and answering ques- tions on long and complex passages, sim
123: torAdam AdamWFP16 BF16 Mixed Decay Clip Dropout T5 (11B) 211 512 0.01 × inverse square root ✓ - - - - - ✓ GPT3 (175B) 32K - 6e-5 ✓ cosine ✓ ✓ ✓ ✓ - mT5 (13B) 1024 1024 0.01 - inverse square root ✓ - - - - - ✓ PanGu-α (200B) - 1024 2e-5 - - - - - - ✓ 
124: ✓ ✓ ✓ ✓ - AlphaCode (41B) 2048 1536+768 1e-4 ✓ cosine decay to 10% ✓ ✓ ✓ ✓ - Chinchilla (70B) 1.5M 2048 1e-4 ✓ cosine decay to 10% ✓ ✓ - - - PaLM (540B) 2048 2048 0.01 - inverse square root ✓ - - - ✓ ✓ × AlexaTM (20B) 2M 1024 1e-4 - linear decay to 5
125: ing. Sequence Optimizers Grad Models Batch Size Length LR Warmup LR_Decay AdaFactor Adam AdamW Clip Dropout WebGPT (175B) BC:512, RM:32 - 6e-5 - - ✓ - - T0 (11B) 1024 1280 1e-3 - - ✓ - ✓ Tk-Instruct (11B) 1024 - 1e-5 - constant - - - - - OPT-IML (175
126: surd to humans but often misclassified by models. COPA [391]: This dataset evaluates a model’s progress in open-domain commonsense causal reasoning. Each question comprises a premise and two alternatives, and the model must select the more plausible 
127: d A multilingual extension of the C4 dataset, mC4 identifies over 100 lan- guages using cld3 from 71 monthly web scrapes of Common Crawl. PILE [291] Pretrain 825GB - Common Crawl, PubMed Central, OpenWebText2, ArXiv, GitHub, Books3, and others Automa
128: ion, QA, classification, etc. xP3 [144] Instructions 81M 71 P3+Multilingual datasets Manual Extending P3 to total 46 languages Super-NaturalInstructions (SNI) [18] Instructions 12.4M 1616 Multiple datasets Manual Extending P3 with additional multi- l
129: mance with fine-tuning on less data Anthropic-HH-RLHF [296] Alignment 142k - - Manual Anthropic-HH-RLHF-2 [168] Alignment 39k - - Manual 5.2.7. Reading Comprehension BoolQ [353]: A dataset derived from Google search queries, BoolQ challenges models t
130: del’s ability to un- derstand a wide variety of reading phenomena. It encourages comprehensive and reliable evaluation of reading comprehen- sion capabilities. RTE [356]: The Recognizing Textual Entailment (RTE) datasets come from a series of annual 
131: th problems, ranging from arithmetic to calculus, and is designed to test the model’s ability to under- stand and solve complex mathematical problems. Math23k [373]: This one challenges a model’s ability to un- derstand and solve mathematical word pr
132: Gen [327], E2E [328], CHID [329], CHID- FC [302] Physical Knowledge and World Understanding PIQA [330], TriviaQA [331], ARC [332], ARC-Easy [332], ARC-Challenge [332], PROST [333], Open- BookQA [334], WebNLG [335], DogWhistle Insider & Outsider [336]
133: asoning MATH [372], Math23k [373], GSM8K [374], MathQA [375], MGSM [376], MultiArith [377], AS- Div [378], MAWPS [379], SVAMP [380] Problem Solving HumanEval [131], DS-1000 [381], MBPP [382], APPS [372], CodeContests [132] Natural Language Inference 
134: laxy Clusters [138], Mineral Groups [138] Dialogue Wizard of Wikipedia [408], Empathetic Dialogues [409], DPC-generated [96] dialogues, ConvAI2 [410], KdConv [411] Topic Classification TNEWS-FC [302], YNAT [305], KLUE-TC [305], CSL [301], CSL-FC [302
135: ple pieces of evidence to evaluate the strategic reasoning ability of AI models, pushing the bound- aries of what machines can understand and answer. 5.2.10. Cross-Lingual Understanding XNLI [388]: A cross-lingual benchmark, XNLI extends the MultiNLI
136: misconceptions. 29  Table 10: An illustration of training datasets and evaluation tasks employed by pre-trained LLMs. Here, “QA” is question-answering, “Clf” is classification, “NLI” is natural language inference, “MT” is machine translation, “RC” is
137: ean blogs, Community sites, News, KiN Korean Wikipedia, Wikipedia (En- glish and Japanese), Modu-Corpus: Mes- senger, News, Spoken and written lan- guage corpus, Web corpus ✓ Yuan 1.0 Common Crawl, SogouT, Sogou News, Baidu Baike, Wikipedia, Books ✓ 
138: nd Books3, OpenWebText2, Stack Exchange, PubMed Abstracts, Wikipedia, PG-19 [242], BookCorpus2, NIH ExPorter, Pile, CC-Stories, RealNews ✓ ✓ ✓ ✓ ✓ AlphaCode Selected GitHub repositories, CodeCon- tests: Codeforces, Description2Code, Co- deNet ✓ Chinc
139: is a short of Super-NaturalInsturctions. Models Training Dataset BIG- bench MMLU BBH RAFT FLAN SNI PromptSource TyDiQA HumanEval MBPP Truthful/ Bias/ Toxicity T0 Pool of Prompts ✓ WebGPT ELI5 [414], ELI5 fact- check [156], TriviaQA [331], ARC-Challen
140: ce, and religion. Contrasting stereotypi- cal bias against language modeling ability provides a valuable tool for understanding and mitigating biases in large language models. 6. Applications Applying Large Language Models (LLMs) to a variety of down
141: in a contextually relevant man- ner. This allows them to perform tasks ranging from simple language translation and question-answering to more complex tasks like summarization, text generation, and even program- ming help [422]. The utility of LLMs i
142: tem, are only as good as the data they have been trained on. Medicine: The application of LLMs in the field of medicine is reshaping healthcare delivery and research. For example, LLMs are increasingly used in clinical decision support systems to pro
143: als, generate exam questions, provide detailed explanations of complex medical topics, and offer personalized feedback to students [435, 436, 437, 438]. They can also simulate patient interactions, enabling students to practice and improve their clin
144: capability in few-shot or zero-shot learning settings, “f” represents the fine-tuned version, and “B” represents the benchmark. Task Dataset/Benchmark Top-1 Top-2 Top-3 Model (Size) Score (N-shots) Model (Size) Score (N-shots) Model (Size) Score (N-s
145: Understanding LAMBADA PaLM (540B) 89.7 (few shot) MT-NLG (530B) 87.15 (few shot) PaLM-2 (Large) 86.9 (one shot) Commonsense Reasoning WinoGrande GPT-4 (-) 87.5 (5-shot) PaLM-2 (Large) 83.0 (one shot) PaLM (540B) 81.1 (zero shot) SIQA LLaMA (65B) 52.3
146: es [442]. For teachers, LLMs can help to create lesson plans and grade assignments and generate diverse and inclusive educational content, significantly saving more time for teaching and student interaction [443, 444]. In language learning, LLMs serv
147: briefing comprehensible and accessible re- search summaries, LLMs can assist researchers in staying up- to-date with the latest findings, even in fields outside their area of expertise [446, 447]. In addition, LLMs can aid scientists in formulating n
148: t corrections, serving as an invaluable tool for both learning and verification purposes [451, 452]. LLMs can be employed to check the valid- ity of mathematical proofs, offering a preliminary filter before human review. While they are not a substitu
149: tionally, LLMs have been evaluated for their ability to generate explanations of legal terms, focusing on improving factual accuracy and relevance by incorporating sentences from case law. By feeding relevant case law into the LLM, the augmented mode
150: ices. Both BloombergGPT and FinGPT show the adaptabil- ity of LLMs to the financial domain, with the former showing 32  the power of custom datasets and the latter emphasizing a data- centric approach and low-rank adaptation techniques for cus- tomiz
151: ]. 7. Challenges and Future Directions LLMs such as GPT-4 and its predecessors have significantly advanced natural language processing. Nevertheless, they also bring along a set of challenges. The computational cost, ad- versarial robustness, and int
152: e into these challenges, shedding light on the on- going and potential efforts to address them. Computational Cost: Training LLMs requires extensive com- putational resources, which increases production costs and raises environmental concerns due to 
153: ng the right balance. Memorization allows the model to remember specific details from its training data, ensuring it can provide accurate answers to precise questions. However, gen- eralization enables the model to make inferences and produce respons
154: ns based on likelihood and offer no solid guaran- tees in terms of reasoning abilities [472]. Hallucinations: LLMs exhibit “hallucinations", where they generate responses that, while sounding plausible, are incor- rect or do not align with the provid
155: responses effectively [474, 32]. Limited Knowledge: Information acquired during pretraining is limited and may become obsolete after some time. Re- training the model using updated data is costly. To generate factually accurate responses people use a
156: -specific data, reducing training resources but facing issues like domain adaptation and catastrophic forgetting, which hinders the retention of original knowledge when learning new tasks. Adversarial Robustness: Large Language Models (LLMs) have sho
157: n sensitive domains. Despite their advanced capabilities, the lack of insight into their operation limits their effectiveness and trustworthiness [479, 480]. Efforts are being made to make LLMs more explainable to promote user trust and to ensure res
158: time processing in Large Lan- guage Models (LLMs) is pivotal for various applications, especially with the rising popularity of mobile AI applications and concerns regarding information security and privacy. However, LLMs often have hundreds of layer
159: - icant hardware challenges due to the increasing computational and memory demands associated with training and deploying these models. GPUs have played a crucial role in meeting the hardware requirements for training LLMs, with the networking indust
160: regulatory oversight to manage the ethical and social challenges accompanying LLMs’ widespread use [485]. For instance, LLMs can generate content that can be used posi- tively or negatively, emphasizing the need for proactive ethical frameworks and p
161: rences of LLMs in zero-shot and few-shot settings, explored the impact of fine-tuning, and com- pared supervised and generalized models and encoder vs. de- coder vs. encoder-decoder architectures. A comprehensive re- view of multi-modal LLMs, retriev
162: ral- purpose language understanding systems, Advances in neural informa- tion processing systems 32 (2019). 1, 24, 29 34  [3] D. Adiwardana, M.-T. Luong, D. R. So, J. Hall, N. Fiedel, R. Thoppilan, Z. Yang, A. Kulshreshtha, G. Nemade, Y. Lu, et al., 
163: , 24 [8] M. E. Peters, M. Neumann, M. Iyyer, M. Gardner, C. Clark, K. Lee, L. Zettlemoyer, Deep contextualized word representations, in: NAACL- HLT, Association for Computational Linguistics, 2018, pp. 2227–2237. 2 [9] M. Lewis, Y. Liu, N. Goyal, M. 
164: o, F. Qi, J. Guan, P. Ke, et al., Cpm-2: Large-scale cost-effective pre-trained lan- guage models, AI Open 2 (2021) 216–224. 2, 8, 25 [13] T. L. Scao, A. Fan, C. Akiki, E. Pavlick, S. Ili´c, D. Hesslow, R. Castagné, A. S. Luccioni, F. Yvon, M. Gallé,
165: 10.11416 (2022). 2, 7, 11, 17, 22, 23, 25, 28, 31 [17] V. Sanh, A. Webson, C. Raffel, S. H. Bach, L. Sutawika, Z. Alyafeai, A. Chaffin, A. Stiegler, T. L. Scao, A. Raja, et al., Multitask prompted training enables zero-shot task generalization, arXiv
166: instructions with human feedback, Advances in Neural In- formation Processing Systems 35 (2022) 27730–27744. 2, 7, 11, 16, 22 [21] H. Touvron, L. Martin, K. Stone, P. Albert, A. Almahairi, Y. Babaei, N. Bashlykov, S. Batra, P. Bhargava, S. Bhosale, e
167: language models, arXiv preprint arXiv:2208.03299 (2022). 2, 17, 18, 33 [26] D. Driess, F. Xia, M. S. Sajjadi, C. Lynch, A. Chowdhery, B. Ichter, A. Wahid, J. Tompson, Q. Vuong, T. Yu, et al., Palm-e: An embodied multimodal language model, arXiv prepr
168: e, X. Li, Y. Shan, Gpt4tools: Teaching large language model to use tools via self-instruction, arXiv preprint arXiv:2305.18752 (2023). 2, 19, 22 [32] E. Saravia, Prompt Engineering Guide, https://github.com/dair- ai/Prompt-Engineering-Guide (12 2022)
169: ing models with over 100 billion parameters, in: Proceedings of the 26th ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery & Data Mining, 2020, pp. 3505– 3506. 2, 5 [37] S. Rajbhandari, J. Rasley, O. Ruwase, Y. He, Zero: Memory optimiza- tio
170: neration, arXiv preprint arXiv:2101.00190 (2021). 2, 20 [42] X. Ma, G. Fang, X. Wang, Llm-pruner: On the structural pruning of large language models, arXiv preprint arXiv:2305.11627 (2023). 2, 21 [43] R. Xu, F. Luo, C. Wang, B. Chang, J. Huang, S. Hu
171: arXiv preprint arXiv:2308.10882 (2023). 2, 17 [47] B. Peng, J. Quesnelle, H. Fan, E. Shippole, Yarn: Efficient con- text window extension of large language models, arXiv preprint arXiv:2309.00071 (2023). 2, 17 [48] M. Guo, J. Ainslie, D. Uthus, S. On
172: ulem, A. P. B. Veyseh, T. H. Nguyen, O. Sainz, E. Agirre, I. Heinz, D. Roth, Recent advances in natural language pro- cessing via large pre-trained language models: A survey, arXiv preprint arXiv:2111.01243 (2021). 2, 3 [53] C. Zhou, Q. Li, C. Li, J.
173: 633 (2023). 2 [58] S. Yin, C. Fu, S. Zhao, K. Li, X. Sun, T. Xu, E. Chen, A survey on multi- modal large language models, arXiv preprint arXiv:2306.13549 (2023). 2, 22 [59] J. J. Webster, C. Kit, Tokenization as the initial phase in nlp, in: COL- ING
174: feai, E. Salesky, C. Raffel, M. Dey, M. Gallé, A. Raja, C. Si, W. Y. Lee, B. Sagot, et al., Between words and char- acters: A brief history of open-vocabulary modeling and tokenization in nlp, arXiv preprint arXiv:2112.10508 (2021). 4 [64] A. Vaswani
175: ention: Fast and memory-efficient exact attention with io-awareness, Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 35 (2022) 16344–16359. 4 [69] K. Hornik, M. Stinchcombe, H. White, Multilayer feedforward networks are universal approximators, Neu
176: er, Glu variants improve transformer, arXiv preprint arXiv:2002.05202 (2020). 4 [75] Y. N. Dauphin, A. Fan, M. Auli, D. Grangier, Language modeling with gated convolutional networks, in: International conference on machine learning, PMLR, 2017, pp. 9
177: com/OpenBMB/BMTrain 4, 5 [82] T. Wolf, L. Debut, V. Sanh, J. Chaumond, C. Delangue, A. Moi, P. Cis- tac, T. Rault, R. Louf, M. Funtowicz, et al., Transformers: State-of-the- art natural language processing, in: Proceedings of the 2020 conference on e
178: . 5 [87] A. Paszke, S. Gross, F. Massa, A. Lerer, J. Bradbury, G. Chanan, T. Killeen, Z. Lin, N. Gimelshein, L. Antiga, et al., Pytorch: An imper- ative style, high-performance deep learning library, Advances in neural information processing systems 
179: ient scaling of language models with mixture-of-experts, in: International Conference on Ma- chine Learning, PMLR, 2022, pp. 5547–5569. 5, 9, 23, 25 [92] X. Ren, P. Zhou, X. Meng, X. Huang, Y. Wang, W. Wang, P. Li, X. Zhang, A. Podolskiy, G. Arshinov
180: ws for neural language models, arXiv preprint arXiv:2001.08361 (2020). 6 [96] J. Hoffmann, S. Borgeaud, A. Mensch, E. Buchatskaya, T. Cai, E. Rutherford, D. d. L. Casas, L. A. Hendricks, J. Welbl, A. Clark, et al., Training compute-optimal large lang
181: N. Stiennon, J. Wu, T. B. Brown, A. Radford, D. Amodei, P. Christiano, G. Irving, Fine-tuning language models from human pref- erences, arXiv preprint arXiv:1909.08593 (2019). 7 [101] S. Kim, S. J. Joo, D. Kim, J. Jang, S. Ye, J. Shin, M. Seo, The co
182: , D. Yu, J. Zhao, I. Shafran, T. L. Griffiths, Y. Cao, K. Narasimhan, Tree of thoughts: Deliberate problem solving with large language mod- els, arXiv preprint arXiv:2305.10601 (2023). 7, 19 [106] N. Houlsby, A. Giurgiu, S. Jastrzebski, B. Morrone, Q
183: , S. Wang, S. Feng, S. Ding, C. Pang, J. Shang, J. Liu, X. Chen, Y. Zhao, Y. Lu, et al., Ernie 3.0: Large-scale knowledge enhanced pre-training for language understanding and generation, arXiv preprint arXiv:2107.02137 (2021). 8, 25 [111] Z. Dai, Z. 
184: X. Zhao, T. Yu, R. Zhang, C. Shen, H. Liu, F. Li, H. Zhu, J. Luo, L. Xu, et al., Yuan 1.0: Large-scale pre-trained language model in zero- shot and few-shot learning, arXiv preprint arXiv:2110.04725 (2021). 8, 23, 25 [116] J. W. Rae, S. Borgeaud, T. 
185: 6 billion parameter autoregressive lan- guage model (2021). 9 [120] P. Micikevicius, S. Narang, J. Alben, G. Diamos, E. Elsen, D. Garcia, B. Ginsburg, M. Houston, O. Kuchaiev, G. Venkatesh, et al., Mixed pre- cision training, arXiv preprint arXiv:171
186: ao, A. Chowdhery, et al., Transcending scaling laws with 0.1% extra compute, arXiv preprint arXiv:2210.11399 (2022). 9, 23, 25 [125] Y. Tay, M. Dehghani, V. Q. Tran, X. Garcia, J. Wei, X. Wang, H. W. Chung, D. Bahri, T. Schuster, S. Zheng, et al., Ul
187: J. Casper, S. Lym, L. McAfee, M. Andersch, 37  M. Shoeybi, B. Catanzaro, Reducing activation recomputation in large transformer models, Proceedings of Machine Learning and Systems 5 (2023). 10 [130] E. Nijkamp, B. Pang, H. Hayashi, L. Tu, H. Wang, Y.
188: ing from demonstrations, arXiv preprint arXiv:2009.07839 (2020). 10 [135] R. Dabre, A. Fujita, Softmax tempering for training neural machine translation models, arXiv preprint arXiv:2009.09372 (2020). 10 [136] Y. Wang, W. Wang, S. Joty, S. C. Hoi, Co
189: azeer, A. Kulshreshtha, H.-T. Cheng, A. Jin, T. Bos, L. Baker, Y. Du, et al., Lamda: Language models for dialog applications, arXiv preprint arXiv:2201.08239 (2022). 11, 25 [141] S. Wu, O. Irsoy, S. Lu, V. Dabravolski, M. Dredze, S. Gehrmann, P. Kamb
190: tuning data cu- ration, arXiv preprint arXiv:2305.14327 (2023). 16 [146] P. Gao, J. Han, R. Zhang, Z. Lin, S. Geng, A. Zhou, W. Zhang, P. Lu, C. He, X. Yue, et al., Llama-adapter v2: Parameter-efficient visual in- struction model, arXiv preprint arXi
191: preprint arXiv:2305.14201 (2023). 16 [152] H. Wang, C. Liu, N. Xi, Z. Qiang, S. Zhao, B. Qin, T. Liu, Huatuo: Tuning llama model with chinese medical knowledge, arXiv preprint arXiv:2304.06975 (2023). 16 [153] C. Xu, Q. Sun, K. Zheng, X. Geng, P. Zha
192: eprint arXiv:2112.09332 (2021). 16, 18, 19, 25, 31 [157] A. Glaese, N. McAleese, M. Tr˛ebacz, J. Aslanides, V. Firoiu, T. Ewalds, M. Rauh, L. Weidinger, M. Chadwick, P. Thacker, et al., Improving alignment of dialogue agents via targeted human judgem
193: 6 [162] H. Liu, C. Sferrazza, P. Abbeel, Languages are rewards: Hindsight fine- tuning using human feedback, arXiv preprint arXiv:2302.02676 (2023). 16 [163] Y. Bai, S. Kadavath, S. Kundu, A. Askell, J. Kernion, A. Jones, A. Chen, A. Goldie, A. Mirho
194: How does llm safety training fail?, arXiv preprint arXiv:2307.02483 (2023). 16 [168] D. Ganguli, L. Lovitt, J. Kernion, A. Askell, Y. Bai, S. Kadavath, B. Mann, E. Perez, N. Schiefer, K. Ndousse, et al., Red teaming lan- guage models to reduce harms:
195: v:2305.01711 (2023). 17 [173] H. Gupta, S. A. Sawant, S. Mishra, M. Nakamura, A. Mitra, S. Mashetty, C. Baral, Instruction tuned models are quick learners, arXiv preprint arXiv:2306.05539 (2023). 17 [174] H. Chen, Y. Zhang, Q. Zhang, H. Yang, X. Hu, 
196: Dong, X. Zhang, S. Huang, W. Wang, F. Wei, Longnet: Scaling transformers to 1,000,000,000 tokens, arXiv preprint arXiv:2307.02486 (2023). 17 [179] Y. Chen, S. Qian, H. Tang, X. Lai, Z. Liu, S. Han, J. Jia, Longlora: Effi- cient fine-tuning of long-co
197: can, G. B. Van Den Driessche, J.-B. Lespiau, B. Damoc, A. Clark, et al., Improving language models by retrieving from trillions of tokens, in: International conference on machine learning, PMLR, 2022, pp. 2206– 2240. 17, 18, 33 [184] W. Zhong, L. Guo
198: dels, arXiv preprint arXiv:2302.00083 (2023). 17, 18, 33 [189] X. Li, X. Qiu, Mot: Pre-thinking and recalling enable chatgpt to self- improve with memory-of-thoughts, arXiv preprint arXiv:2305.05181 (2023). 17 [190] D. Schuurmans, Memory augmented la
199: . 18 [195] B. Wang, W. Ping, P. Xu, L. McAfee, Z. Liu, M. Shoeybi, Y. Dong, O. Kuchaiev, B. Li, C. Xiao, et al., Shall we pretrain autoregressive language models with retrieval? a comprehensive study, arXiv preprint arXiv:2304.06762 (2023). 18 [196] 
200: ugmented language model pre-training, in: International conference on machine learning, PMLR, 2020, pp. 3929–3938. 18 [202] S. Hofstätter, J. Chen, K. Raman, H. Zamani, Fid-light: Efficient and ef- fective retrieval-augmented text generation, in: Pro
201: oning with large language models, arXiv preprint arXiv:2304.09842 (2023). 18, 19, 22 [207] B. Paranjape, S. Lundberg, S. Singh, H. Hajishirzi, L. Zettlemoyer, M. T. Ribeiro, Art: Automatic multi-step reasoning and tool-use for large lan- guage models
202: F. Hong, B. Li, C. Hu, Z. Chen, J. Zhang, On the tool manipu- lation capability of open-source large language models, arXiv preprint arXiv:2305.16504 (2023). 18 [213] Y. Qin, S. Liang, Y. Ye, K. Zhu, L. Yan, Y. Lu, Y. Lin, X. Cong, X. Tang, B. Qian, 
203: ion Systems Engineering 58 (2016) 367–370. 19 [218] M. Campbell, A. J. Hoane Jr, F.-h. Hsu, Deep blue, Artificial intelligence 134 (1-2) (2002) 57–83. 19 [219] S. Hong, X. Zheng, J. Chen, Y. Cheng, J. Wang, C. Zhang, Z. Wang, S. K. S. Yau, Z. Lin, L.
204: J. J. Hong, Z. Wang, D. Z. Wang, Z. Hu, Reason- ing with language model is planning with world model, arXiv preprint arXiv:2305.14992 (2023). 19, 33 [224] W. Yao, S. Heinecke, J. C. Niebles, Z. Liu, Y. Feng, L. Xue, R. Murthy, Z. Chen, J. Zhang, D. A
205: Thomason, A. Garg, Progprompt: Generating situated robot task plans using large language models, in: 2023 IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA), IEEE, 2023, pp. 11523–11530. 19, 33 [228] W. Yu, N. Gileadi, C. Fu, S. Kirmani,
206: vanshi, K. Sikka, X. Lin, B. Lee, H.-P. Chiu, A. Velasquez, Say- nav: Grounding large language models for dynamic planning to navi- gation in new environments, arXiv preprint arXiv:2309.04077 (2023). 20 [233] C. H. Song, J. Wu, C. Washington, B. M. S
207: v preprint arXiv:2103.10385 (2021). 20 [238] G. Chen, F. Liu, Z. Meng, S. Liang, Revisiting parameter-efficient tun- ing: Are we really there yet?, arXiv preprint arXiv:2202.07962 (2022). 20 [239] Y. Wang, S. Mukherjee, X. Liu, J. Gao, A. H. Awadalla
208: 243] Z.-R. Zhang, C. Tan, H. Xu, C. Wang, J. Huang, S. Huang, To- wards adaptive prefix tuning for parameter-efficient language model fine-tuning, arXiv preprint arXiv:2305.15212 (2023). 20 [244] E. B. Zaken, S. Ravfogel, Y. Goldberg, Bitfit: Simple 
209: ing quantization and pruning, Advances in Neural In- formation Processing Systems 35 (2022) 4475–4488. 20 [249] C. Lee, J. Jin, T. Kim, H. Kim, E. Park, Owq: Lessons learned from ac- tivation outliers for weight quantization in large language models,
210: Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, 2017, pp. 5955–5963. 21 [254] J. Kim, J. H. Lee, S. Kim, J. Park, K. M. Yoo, S. J. Kwon, D. Lee, Memory-efficient fine-tuning of compressed large language models via sub-4-bit integer quantizatio
211: 10880–10895. 21 [259] J.-B. Alayrac, J. Donahue, P. Luc, A. Miech, I. Barr, Y. Hasson, K. Lenc, A. Mensch, K. Millican, M. Reynolds, et al., Flamingo: a visual lan- guage model for few-shot learning, Advances in Neural Information Pro- cessing System
212: understanding, arXiv preprint arXiv:2306.02858 (2023). 21 [265] X. Mei, C. Meng, H. Liu, Q. Kong, T. Ko, C. Zhao, M. D. Plumbley, Y. Zou, W. Wang, Wavcaps: A chatgpt-assisted weakly-labelled au- dio captioning dataset for audio-language multimodal re
213: : Towards general-purpose vision-language models with instruction tuning, arXiv preprint arXiv:2305.06500 (2023). 22 [270] Z. Xu, Y. Shen, L. Huang, Multiinstruct: Improving multi-modal zero- shot learning via instruction tuning, arXiv preprint arXiv
214: 23 (2023). 22 [275] R. Zhang, J. Han, A. Zhou, X. Hu, S. Yan, P. Lu, H. Li, P. Gao, Y. Qiao, Llama-adapter: Efficient fine-tuning of language models with zero-init attention, arXiv preprint arXiv:2303.16199 (2023). 22 [276] A. Radford, J. W. Kim, T. 
215: ing chatgpt for multimodal rea- soning and action, arXiv preprint arXiv:2303.11381 (2023). 22 [281] T. Wang, J. Zhang, J. Fei, Y. Ge, H. Zheng, Y. Tang, Z. Li, M. Gao, S. Zhao, Y. Shan, et al., Caption anything: Interactive image descrip- tion with d
216: for visual question answering, in: Proceedings of the IEEE/CVF conference on computer vision and pattern recognition, 2019, pp. 6281– 6290. 22 [286] H. You, R. Sun, Z. Wang, L. Chen, G. Wang, H. A. Ayyubi, K.- W. Chang, S.-F. Chang, Idealgpt: Iterati
217: el, S. Levine, D. Song, Koala: A dialogue model for academic research, Blog post (April 2023). URL https://bair.berkeley.edu/blog/2023/04/03/koala/ 25 [291] L. Gao, S. Biderman, S. Black, L. Golding, T. Hoppe, C. Foster, J. Phang, H. He, A. Thite, N.
218: rint arXiv:2212.09689 (2022). 28 [296] Y. Bai, A. Jones, K. Ndousse, A. Askell, A. Chen, N. DasSarma, D. Drain, S. Fort, D. Ganguli, T. Henighan, et al., Training a helpful and harmless assistant with reinforcement learning from human feedback, arXiv
219: al., Cuge: A chinese language understanding and gen- eration evaluation benchmark, arXiv preprint arXiv:2112.13610 (2021). 29 [301] L. Xu, H. Hu, X. Zhang, L. Li, C. Cao, Y. Li, Y. Xu, K. Sun, D. Yu, C. Yu, et al., Clue: A chinese language understand
220: age understanding evaluation, arXiv preprint arXiv:2105.09680 (2021). 29 [306] S. Reddy, D. Chen, C. D. Manning, Coqa: A conversational question answering challenge, Transactions of the Association for Computational Linguistics 7 (2019) 249–266. 25, 
221: ://quoradata.quora.com/ First-Quora-Dataset-Release-Question-Pairs. 29 [312] R. Rudinger, J. Naradowsky, B. Leonard, B. Van Durme, Gender bias in coreference resolution, arXiv preprint arXiv:1804.09301 (2018). 29 [313] M.-C. De Marneffe, M. Simons, J
222: 2018 conference on empiri- cal methods in natural language processing, 2018, pp. 4946–4951. 29 [317] B. Liu, D. Niu, H. Wei, J. Lin, Y. He, K. Lai, Y. Xu, Matching arti- cle pairs with graphical decomposition and convolutions, arXiv preprint arXiv:18
223: 1T03, Philadelphia, Penn.: Linguistic Data Consor- tium (2011). 29 [322] D. Vilares, C. Gómez-Rodríguez, Head-qa: A healthcare dataset for complex reasoning, arXiv preprint arXiv:1906.04701 (2019). 29 [323] S. L. Blodgett, L. Green, B. O’Connor, Demo
224: iverse text gener- ation with planning-based hierarchical variational model, arXiv preprint arXiv:1908.06605 (2019). 29 [328] J. Novikova, O. Dušek, V. Rieser, The e2e dataset: New challenges for end-to-end generation, arXiv preprint arXiv:1706.09254
225: llette, C. Paik, A. Roncone, K. Kann, Prost: Phys- ical reasoning of objects through space and time, arXiv preprint arXiv:2106.03634 (2021). 29 [334] T. Mihaylov, P. Clark, T. Khot, A. Sabharwal, Can a suit of armor con- duct electricity? a new datas
226: , M. Yatskar, W.-t. Yih, Y. Choi, P. Liang, L. Zettlemoyer, Quac: Question answering in context, arXiv preprint arXiv:1808.07036 (2018). 27, 29 [339] M. Geva, D. Khashabi, E. Segal, T. Khot, D. Roth, J. Berant, Did aristo- tle use a laptop? a questio
227: 74061–74071. 29 [343] C. Xu, J. Pei, H. Wu, Y. Liu, C. Li, Matinf: A jointly labeled large-scale dataset for classification, question answering and summarization, arXiv preprint arXiv:2004.12302 (2020). 29 [344] K. Sakaguchi, R. L. Bras, C. Bhagavatu
228: ing challenge targeting commonsense knowledge, arXiv preprint arXiv:1811.00937 (2018). 27, 29 [349] M. Sap, H. Rashkin, D. Chen, R. LeBras, Y. Choi, Socialiqa: 42  Commonsense reasoning about social interactions, arXiv preprint arXiv:1904.09728 (2019
229: iang, Know what you don’t know: Unanswer- able questions for squad, arXiv preprint arXiv:1806.03822 (2018). 28, 29 [355] D. Dua, Y. Wang, P. Dasigi, G. Stanovsky, S. Singh, M. Gardner, Drop: A reading comprehension benchmark requiring discrete reason
230: 66 (2018). 28, 29 [360] Y. Cui, T. Liu, Z. Yang, Z. Chen, W. Ma, W. Che, S. Wang, G. Hu, A sentence cloze dataset for chinese machine reading comprehension, arXiv preprint arXiv:2004.03116 (2020). 29 [361] Y. Li, T. Liu, D. Li, Q. Li, J. Shi, Y. Wang
231: (2019) 453–466. 29 [364] C. C. Shao, T. Liu, Y. Lai, Y. Tseng, S. Tsai, Drcd: A chinese ma- chine reading comprehension dataset, arXiv preprint arXiv:1806.00920 (2018). 29 [365] W. He, K. Liu, J. Liu, Y. Lyu, S. Zhao, X. Xiao, Y. Liu, Y. Wang, H. Wu,
232: te, Qa4mre 2011-2013: Overview of question answering for machine read- ing evaluation, in: Information Access Evaluation. Multilinguality, Mul- timodality, and Visualization: 4th International Conference of the CLEF Initiative, CLEF 2013, Valencia, S
233: ng, 2017, pp. 845–854. 28, 29 [374] K. Cobbe, V. Kosaraju, M. Bavarian, M. Chen, H. Jun, L. Kaiser, M. Plappert, J. Tworek, J. Hilton, R. Nakano, et al., Training verifiers to solve math word problems, arXiv preprint arXiv:2110.14168 (2021). 29 [375]
234: ository, in: Proceedings of the 2016 conference of the north american chapter of the association for computa- tional linguistics: human language technologies, 2016, pp. 1152–1157. 29 [380] A. Patel, S. Bhattamishra, N. Goyal, Are nlp models really ab
235: corpus for sentence understanding through inference, arXiv preprint arXiv:1704.05426 (2017). 29 [385] R. T. McCoy, E. Pavlick, T. Linzen, Right for the wrong reasons: Diag- nosing syntactic heuristics in natural language inference, arXiv preprint arX
236: the details, just the summary!, Topic-Aware Convolutional Neural Networks for Extreme Summarization. ArXiv, abs (1808). 29 [391] E. M. Ponti, G. Glavaš, O. Majewska, Q. Liu, I. Vuli´c, A. Korhonen, Xcopa: A multilingual dataset for causal commonsense
237: rXiv:2109.07958 (2021). 29 [396] I. Augenstein, C. Lioma, D. Wang, L. C. Lima, C. Hansen, C. Hansen, J. G. Simonsen, Multifc: A real-world multi-domain dataset for evidence-based fact checking of claims, arXiv preprint arXiv:1909.03242 (2019). 29 [39
238: ebiasing methods, arXiv preprint arXiv:1804.06876 (2018). 29 [402] N. Nangia, C. Vania, R. Bhalerao, S. R. Bowman, Crows-pairs: A chal- lenge dataset for measuring social biases in masked language models, arXiv preprint arXiv:2010.00133 (2020). 29 [4
239: man, H. Barry, H. Matthias, J. Eric, K. Tom, et al., Findings of the 2020 conference on machine translation (wmt20), in: Proceedings of the Fifth Conference on Machine Translation, Association for Compu- tational Linguistics„ 2020, pp. 1–55. 29 [407]
240: u, C. Zheng, K. Huang, M. Huang, X. Zhu, Kdconv: A chinese multi-domain dialogue dataset towards multi-turn knowledge-driven conversation, arXiv preprint arXiv:2004.04100 (2020). 29 [412] L. CO, Iflytek: a multiple categories chinese text classifier.
241: ing and multi- tasking structured knowledge grounding with text-to-text language mod- els, arXiv preprint arXiv:2201.05966 (2022). 31 [417] Q. Ye, B. Y. Lin, X. Ren, Crossfit: A few-shot learning challenge for cross-task generalization in nlp, arXiv 
242: bling, in: Proceedings of the 2019 Conference of the North Amer- ican Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics: Human Language Technologies, Volume 1 (Long and Short Papers), Associa- tion for Computational Linguistics, Minneapolis, M
243: on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining, 2023, pp. 5792–5793. 31 [424] K. Pandya, M. Holia, Automating customer service using langchain: Building custom open-source gpt chatbot for organizations, arXiv preprint arXiv:2310.05421 (2023). 31 [425] J. Li,
244: ng the potential of chat-gpt as a supportive tool for sialendoscopy clinical decision making and patient information support, European Archives of Oto-Rhino-Laryngology (2023) 1–6. 31 [429] S. Montagna, S. Ferretti, L. C. Klopfenstein, A. Florio, M. 
245: ired for biomedical engineering and research, Annals of Biomedical Engineering (2023) 1–4. 31 [434] Y. Du, S. Zhao, Y. Chen, R. Bai, J. Liu, H. Wu, H. Wang, B. Qin, The calla dataset: Probing llms’ interactive knowledge acquisition from chi- nese med
246: eiana, M. Dettori, A. Arghittu, A. Azara, G. Gabutti, P. Castiglia, Artificial intelligence and public health: Evaluating chatgpt responses to vaccination myths and misconceptions, Vaccines 11 (7) (2023) 1217. 31 [440] L. De Angelis, F. Baglivo, G. A
247: Kasneci, K. Seßler, S. Küchemann, M. Bannert, D. Dementieva, F. Fischer, U. Gasser, G. Groh, S. Günnemann, E. Hüllermeier, et al., Chatgpt for good? on opportunities and challenges of large language models for education, Learning and individual diffe
248: egrity of the scientific discourse in jeopardy?, arXiv preprint arXiv:2311.06981 (2023). 32 [448] Y. Zheng, H. Y. Koh, J. Ju, A. T. Nguyen, L. T. May, G. I. Webb, S. Pan, Large language models for scientific synthesis, inference and explana- tion, ar
249: d language models, arXiv preprint arXiv:2306.15626 (2023). 32 [454] K. M. Collins, A. Q. Jiang, S. Frieder, L. Wong, M. Zilka, U. Bhatt, T. Lukasiewicz, Y. Wu, J. B. Tenenbaum, W. Hart, et al., Evaluating language models for mathematics through inter
250: benchmark for measuring legal reasoning in large language models, arXiv preprint arXiv:2308.11462 (2023). 32 [459] J. Cui, Z. Li, Y. Yan, B. Chen, L. Yuan, Chatlaw: Open-source legal large language model with integrated external knowledge bases, arXi
251: n human-robot collaboration with chatgpt, IEEE Access (2023). 33 [465] Y. Ding, X. Zhang, C. Paxton, S. Zhang, Leveraging commonsense knowledge from large language models for task and motion planning, in: RSS 2023 Workshop on Learning for Task and Mo
252: 021) 107–115. 33 [470] M. Tänzer, S. Ruder, M. Rei, Memorisation versus generalisation in pre- trained language models, arXiv preprint arXiv:2105.00828 (2021). 33 [471] S. M. West, M. Whittaker, K. Crawford, Discriminating systems, AI Now (2019) 1–33
253: heng, P. He, W. Chen, Y. Wang, H. Poon, J. Gao, Adversar- ial training for large neural language models, ArXiv (April 2020). URL https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/ publication/adversarial-training-for-large-neural-language-models/ 34 [477] E. 
254: rve privacy?, in: Proceedings of the 2022 ACM Conference on Fairness, Accountability, and Transparency, 2022, pp. 2280–2292. 34 [482] R. Plant, V. Giuffrida, D. Gkatzia, You are what you write: Pre- serving privacy in the era of large language models
255: uage models: Guiding responsible development and deployment, arXiv preprint arXiv:2308.02678 (2023). 34 [487] J. Mökander, J. Schuett, H. R. Kirk, L. Floridi, Auditing large language models: a three-layered approach, AI and Ethics (2023) 1–31. 34 46
